<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Matthias Kestenholz: Posts about feincms</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/category-feincms//atom.xml" rel="self" /><link href="https://406.ch/writing/category-feincms/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/category-feincms/</id><updated>2020-09-21T12:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Matthias Kestenholz</name></author><entry><title>Embedding videos in feincms3</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/embedding-videos-in-feincms3/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/embedding-videos-in-feincms3/</id><published>2020-09-21T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-21T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Embedding videos in feincms3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using &lt;a href="https://oembed.com/"&gt;oEmbed&lt;/a&gt; services for about 10 years now to embed content from YouTube and Vimeo on other sites, first using &lt;a href="https://github.com/feincms/feincms-oembed/"&gt;feincms-oembed&lt;/a&gt; and later using &lt;a href="https://feincms3.readthedocs.io/en/latest/ref/plugins.html#module-feincms3.plugins.external"&gt;feincms3.plugins.external&lt;/a&gt;. This worked well enough despite some problems such as &lt;a href="https://embed.ly/"&gt;Embed.ly&lt;/a&gt; introducing API keys and &lt;a href="https://noembed.com/"&gt;Noembed&lt;/a&gt; being more or less unmaintained since 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the requirement to fetch data from a different service always bothered me, especially since all I wanted (most of the time) was to generate a bare &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;iframe&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; containing the embed, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/jazzband/django-embed-video/"&gt;django-embed-video&lt;/a&gt; was almost what I needed but it had some worrysome thumbnail fetching code in there; also I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand the reason for defining backends, dynamically importing them etc. when all I wanted was a function where I would get back some HTML when passing a supported URL, or nothing if the URL wasn&amp;rsquo;t supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I really like writing code&lt;sup id="fnref:nih"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:nih"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; here&amp;rsquo;s my solution to embedding YouTube and Vimeo videos as a part of feincms3, &lt;a href="https://github.com/matthiask/feincms3/blob/main/feincms3/embedding.py"&gt;feincms3.embedding&lt;/a&gt;. Since it doesn&amp;rsquo;t depend on an external service (except the obvious ones) it is &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ"&gt;never gonna give you up&lt;/a&gt; if you just call:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from feincms3.embedding import embed
html = embed("https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dQw4w9WgXcQ")
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:nih"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just a really strong &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Not_invented_here"&gt;NIH syndrome&lt;/a&gt;. Either way, since most other content providers are sadly/luckily irrelevant for the sites I help create and maintain it should be fine.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:nih" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>feincms may still be relevant</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/feincms-may-still-be-relevant/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/feincms-may-still-be-relevant/</id><published>2020-09-17T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;feincms may still be relevant&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following text &amp;ldquo;feincms&amp;rdquo; denotes the feincms-family of tools. Just to reiterate, new
projects should use &lt;a href="https://feincms3.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"&gt;feincms3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 10 years ago there existed a few Django-based CMS. If someone didn&amp;rsquo;t already know which to choose, the following three systems were seen as reasonable choices&lt;sup id="fnref:choices"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:choices"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://mezzanine.jupo.org/"&gt;Mezzanine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. There were some doubts about Mezzanine&amp;rsquo;s maintenance status, see &lt;a href="https://github.com/jazzband-roadies/help/issues/178"&gt;this Jazzband issue&lt;/a&gt; but they were unfounded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.django-cms.org/"&gt;django CMS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Perhaps the best known Django-based CMS back then and maybe now too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20110925190435/http://feincms.org:80/"&gt;feincms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:feincms-archive"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:feincms-archive"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The landscape has changed. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://wagtail.io/"&gt;Wagtail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; hasn&amp;rsquo;t been the new kid on the block anymore for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been following the development of those CMS more or less closely over the years and am convinced that all of them are good choices for starting new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re still using &lt;a href="https://github.com/feincms/feincms/"&gt;feincms&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href="https://feinheit.ch/"&gt;Feinheit&lt;/a&gt;; or more often &lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/the-other-future-of-feincms-django-content-editor-and-feincms3/"&gt;django-content-editor and feincms3&lt;/a&gt;, especially for new projects. Since the development of the feincms 1.x line has slowed down to maintenance mode and the community of feincms3 is really small you might ask why we&amp;rsquo;re still sticking with those tools &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;re certainly asking it ourselves from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="feincms3 / django-content-editor interface" src="https://406.ch/media/cabinet/2020/09/django-content-editor.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of reasons why feincms is still relevant:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s only one autogenerated administration interface to maintain and explain to users &amp;ndash; the stock Django administration interface. It works really well and since it&amp;rsquo;s maintained by the Django community it has received a steady stream of (small but important) improvements over the years. feincms has always been in the position to profit from those improvements immediately since it does not come with its own administration interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;feincms is generally very stable. Especially the django-content-editor / feincms3 combination consists of very little code&lt;sup id="fnref:loc"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:loc"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which allows us to easily use the latest and best version of Django and other packages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Django makes it straightforward to manage the database content and structure. If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever imported content from a different CMS you know how tidy a database managed by Django can be, a stark contrast to the JSON blobs or PHP serialization results used by other content management systems. feincms doesn&amp;rsquo;t invent its own database structure either but allows continuing this success story into the realm of flow content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;feincms does not insist to take over the whole site, and can be used to manage parts only. feincms also allows integrating other models and apps without much boilerplate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;feincms exposes its building blocks and the foundation, making it relatively easy to use the same content in different ways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/37567459-designing-connected-content"&gt;Designing Connected Content&lt;/a&gt; book gave me a way to better formulate these thoughts. I&amp;rsquo;d recommend it to everyone who sometimes has to defend using Django instead of &amp;ldquo;nicer&amp;rdquo; CMS such as Wordpress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;feincms will probably never get back to being one of the major Django-based CMS. That&amp;rsquo;s alright (no, really!) &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; I hope that it keeps its place in the toolkit of a few Django developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have to build a blog or cms alongside a django project (ie. entreprise blog), django-content-editor from @suppensud is a nifty, minimal and unobtrusive package to manage and dnd custom content blocks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/providenz/status/961906127477895168"&gt;by @providenz on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:choices"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I do not step on too many toes with this formulation.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:choices" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:feincms-archive"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wayback machine link, the current website redirects to this blog.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:feincms-archive" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:loc"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://dwheeler.com/sloccount/"&gt;SLOCCount&lt;/a&gt; counts 88&amp;lsquo;039 lines in Wagtail, 73&amp;lsquo;022 lines in django CMS, 45&amp;lsquo;306 lines in Mezzanine, and just 4012 lines in feincms3 and django-content-editor; all values including tests, in current Git repositories as of 2020-09-16. Not including dependencies; they would skew the results even more given that e.g. &lt;a href="https://github.com/django-treebeard/django-treebeard"&gt;django-treebeard&lt;/a&gt; has 10 times more code than &lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/django-tree-queries/"&gt;django-tree-queries&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:loc" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>I just learned about Wagtail's StreamField</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/i-just-learned-about-wagtail-s-streamfield/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/i-just-learned-about-wagtail-s-streamfield/</id><published>2018-09-30T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-09-30T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;I just learned about Wagtail&amp;rsquo;s StreamField&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just read and learned about &lt;a href="https://torchbox.com/blog/rich-text-fields-and-faster-horses/"&gt;Wagtail&amp;rsquo;s StreamField&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; interesting. Good to see that more Django-based CMS systems are leaving the oversized rich text editor behind, as FeinCMS/feincms3 does since 2009.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Bringing FeinCMS and django-content-editor/feincms3 closer together</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/bringing-feincms-and-django-content-editorfeincms3-closer-together/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/bringing-feincms-and-django-content-editorfeincms3-closer-together/</id><published>2018-09-23T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-09-23T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Bringing FeinCMS and django-content-editor/feincms3 closer together&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had more time those are the features I would try to implement next:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reimplement FeinCMS&amp;rsquo;s TreeEditor using django-mptt&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://django-mptt.github.io/django-mptt/admin.html#mptt-admin-draggablempttadmin"&gt;DraggableMPTTAdmin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a big effort. The toggleable booleans are probably the only feature from the &lt;code&gt;TreeEditor&lt;/code&gt; that haven&amp;rsquo;t made it into django-mptt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Add features to django-content-editor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Moving content blocks as a group&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be awesome if it was possible to collapse the content blocks&amp;rsquo; fieldsets, mark consecutive blocks and move them as a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Adding content blocks in the middle and improving reordering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now it&amp;rsquo;s only possible to add new content blocks at the end; only after saving is it allowed to move new blocks in-between pre-existing content. This is a limitation of django&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;InlineFormset&lt;/code&gt; respectively of django-content-editor&amp;rsquo;s naive reuse which expects new inline instances to always be ordered after existing forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that by using flexbox&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;order&lt;/code&gt; attribute and some custom JavaScript code it should be possible to keep the ordering of inlines stable in the HTML code. If that was true the backend code wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to be changed, which would also keep maintenance lower for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;ItemEditor&lt;/code&gt; from FeinCMS supports adding content in the middle, but if users dynamically add and remove other content blocks (which makes Django&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;inlines.js&lt;/code&gt; renumber all formsets) a crash when saving is almost a certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reimplement FeinCMS&amp;rsquo;s ItemEditor using &lt;a href="https://django-content-editor.readthedocs.io/"&gt;django-content-editor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be too hard either. Right now the content editor&amp;rsquo;s JavaScript code assumes too much about the &lt;code&gt;related_name&lt;/code&gt; field of plugins&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;parent&lt;/code&gt; foreign key, but apart from this the content editor&amp;rsquo;s code should work right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In FeinCMS-land, the &lt;code&gt;ItemEditorInline&lt;/code&gt; should extend the &lt;code&gt;ContentEditorInline&lt;/code&gt;. The biggest pain point with the &lt;code&gt;ItemEditorInline&lt;/code&gt; is that it supports adding additional fields to individual instances&amp;rsquo; forms (the &lt;code&gt;admin_fields&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href="https://feincms-django-cms.readthedocs.io/en/latest/integration.html#additional-customization-possibilities"&gt;feature&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;code&gt;ApplicationContent&lt;/code&gt; requires this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;There should be a good way to undo changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enough said.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>What did FeinCMS get right?</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/what-did-feincms-get-right/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/what-did-feincms-get-right/</id><published>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;What did FeinCMS get right?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of things FeinCMS got right. The list will never be exhaustive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sites are different&lt;/em&gt;. Building a framework and not a single product covering all use cases is still a good idea. Also, we are building on top of Django, so we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to sell the advantages of using a framework compared to using a ready-made CMS which looks better when comparing features but not when really working with it day to day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ItemEditor and its structuring of content (e.g. keeping images separate, rigidly clean HTML blobs) is still the right way to do it, even though I can&amp;rsquo;t disagree that the interface for editors might be improved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making things reusable (the ItemEditor for blog entries, the TreeEditor for any tree shaped data) was the right thing to do. The tree editor code has its descendants (pun intended) everywhere, in django-mptt, in django-treebeard and also in other projects. It also seems to me that the same ideas ItemEditor implements have found their way into other projects, although I&amp;rsquo;m certainly not claiming credit for all those.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Staying close to Django&amp;rsquo;s administration interface instead of diverging (and having to rebuild functionality at great effort and cost) was the right decision to make and helps FeinCMS reach compatibility much faster with new versions of Django and other software FeinCMS depends on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making it extensible, and keeping specialized content types out of the main repository lowered the activity in the repository, especially when compared to some other content management systems. This means less pressure on maintainers and it communicates clearly that writing your own content types is not only possible but expected and well supported.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series, &lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/the-future-of-feincms/"&gt;The future of FeinCMS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The state of things in FeinCMS 1.x land</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/the-state-of-things-in-feincms-1x-land/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/the-state-of-things-in-feincms-1x-land/</id><published>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The state of things in FeinCMS 1.x land&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/feincms/feincms"&gt;FeinCMS&lt;/a&gt; is still in active use, but not very actively developed. This does not have to be a bad thing &amp;ndash; FeinCMS is compatible with the recently released Django 2.1 back to Django 1.7, it works well and it&amp;rsquo;s pain points are generally well known by long time users. Slow development also means minimal breakage because of new incompatibilities, not bad either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, here&amp;rsquo;s a list of things with I find bothersome when working with FeinCMS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The extension mechanism and &lt;code&gt;create_content_type&lt;/code&gt; are brittle. Many hacks and workarounds and fumbling with Django&amp;rsquo;s internals were necessary over the years to avoid invalid and/or incomplete model meta information. Also, testing the dynamic creation of models is hard to test and most breakages were very hard to reproduce.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has a few features which make it hard to know what&amp;rsquo;s going on. There&amp;rsquo;s no single place to look if you want to know what fields the page model has. There&amp;rsquo;s no place no look if you want to know what happens when processing a request because request and response processors and also the content types themselves all have ways to interfere and even short circuit request processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The implicitness of the automatic registration of content type inlines with the administration interface made it necessary to invent new hacks (&lt;code&gt;feincms_item_editor_form&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;feincms_item_editor_inline&lt;/code&gt;) to still be able to customize the inline class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Models and rendering is coupled too closely. Adding a &lt;code&gt;render()&lt;/code&gt; method to content type models works well enough for small-to-medium sized websites, but falls apart quickly for infrastructure projects. The coupling itself does not prevent people from implementing better and more decoupled solutions, but doing the ugly thing is just too easy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;ApplicationContent&lt;/code&gt; way of integrating apps was nice, but mostly you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want more than one app per page anyway. The complexity cost of this flexibility e.g. for running apps (calling the resolver ourselves) and for reversing URLs (impossible to use Django&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;reverse()&lt;/code&gt; function directly) is higher than necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To be honest I don&amp;rsquo;t understand the &lt;code&gt;feincms.extensions.translations&lt;/code&gt; extension and its redirect mechanisms anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The reusability of the base model and the page view is enormously bad. Reimplementing the view by calling all processors and content types&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;process()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;finalize()&lt;/code&gt; methods and so on is just horrible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, FeinCMS is used in a few flagship projects which we&amp;rsquo;re still actively developing, which means that FeinCMS won&amp;rsquo;t be going away for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series, &lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/the-future-of-feincms/"&gt;The future of FeinCMS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The other future of FeinCMS: django-content-editor and feincms3</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/the-other-future-of-feincms-django-content-editor-and-feincms3/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/the-other-future-of-feincms-django-content-editor-and-feincms3/</id><published>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The other future of FeinCMS: django-content-editor and feincms3&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FeinCMS ItemEditor code lives on in a new project, &lt;a href="https://django-content-editor.readthedocs.io/"&gt;django-content-editor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast &lt;a href="https://feincms3.readthedocs.io/"&gt;feincms3&lt;/a&gt; is a completely new project, which was the result of starting to build websites with a stripped down environment of django-content-editor and django-mptt&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;feincms3 avoids many of the downsides of FeinCMS 1.x by doing less. At first sight it sounds like building a website with feincms3 will be more work. In my view this does not have to be, since feincms3 offers more direct ways of achieving the same results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;feincms3 addresses &lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/the-state-of-things-in-feincms-1x-land/"&gt;FeinCMS&amp;rsquo; issues&lt;/a&gt; by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It does not offer concrete models, only mixins. Because of this, all problems with dynamic model creation and the extensions mechanism simply disappear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You write the page model yourself, so you&amp;rsquo;ll know what fields it has.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No request and response processors, and plugins (content types in FeinCMS 1.x) do not have any ways of interferring with request and response processing. This makes at all times obvious what&amp;rsquo;s going to happen when processing a request. Redirects? Easy, DIY in your own, short view function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The automatic creation of inlines for the admin interface is gone. This avoids the custom &lt;code&gt;feincms_item_editor_inline&lt;/code&gt; protocol, and its coupling of models and the administration interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Models do not have a render method. Instead, there&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href="https://feincms3.readthedocs.io/en/latest/build-your-cms.html#rendering-and-templates"&gt;renderer&lt;/a&gt; where you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to register plugins. This makes it straightforward to use different renderers for different purposes, and the preferred way to achieve this is obvious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new application mixin (replacing FeinCMS 1.x &lt;code&gt;ApplicationContent&lt;/code&gt;) works with Django&amp;rsquo;s own &lt;code&gt;reverse()&lt;/code&gt; without any monkey patching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And last but not least feincms3 does not only not ship a complicated view function, it does not ship a view function &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. The reason is that &lt;a href="https://feincms3.readthedocs.io/en/latest/build-your-cms.html#views-and-urls"&gt;writing feincms3 views is extremely straightforward&lt;/a&gt; and mostly requires only a few feincms3-specific lines of code in real-world projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TreeEditor has been added to &lt;a href="https://django-mptt.readthedocs.io/en/latest/admin.html#mptt-admin-draggablempttadmin"&gt;django-mptt&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;code&gt;DraggableMPTTAdmin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have since moved to &lt;a href="https://github.com/matthiask/django-tree-queries"&gt;django-tree-queries&lt;/a&gt;, but now&amp;rsquo;s not the time for this story. Search through feincms3&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://feincms3.readthedocs.io/en/latest/project/changelog.html"&gt;CHANGELOG&lt;/a&gt; if you want to know more right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is part of a series, &lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/the-future-of-feincms/"&gt;The future of FeinCMS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The future of FeinCMS</title><link href="https://406.ch/writing/the-future-of-feincms/" rel="alternate" /><id>https://406.ch/writing/the-future-of-feincms/</id><published>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-09-22T12:00:00+00:00</updated><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The future of FeinCMS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent exchange in an &lt;a href="https://github.com/feincms/feincms-elephantblog/issues/68"&gt;issue in the elephantblog repository on Github asking whether the project was still alive&lt;/a&gt; and my own work on &lt;a href="https://feincms3.readthedocs.io"&gt;feincms3&lt;/a&gt; made me think about the need to clarify my position on the future of &lt;a href="https://github.com/feincms/feincms"&gt;FeinCMS 1.x&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the issue I wrote that it (meaning elephantblog) is mostly in maintenance mode and not actively developed anymore, and I also pointed people towards feincms3 for new projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of things FeinCMS 1.x got right and there are things that could be better or I could have handled better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FeinCMS is used in a few flagship projects which we&amp;rsquo;re still actively developing, which means that FeinCMS won&amp;rsquo;t be going away for years to come. That being said, for new CMS projects I&amp;rsquo;m more likely to use django-content-editor and feincms3. This series of blog posts offers an appreciation for my most successful open source project and hopefully also offers insights into my plans and the reasoning behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/the-state-of-things-in-feincms-1x-land/"&gt;The state of things in FeinCMS 1.x land&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/what-did-feincms-get-right/"&gt;What did FeinCMS get right?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/the-other-future-of-feincms-django-content-editor-and-feincms3/"&gt;The other future of FeinCMS: django-content-editor and feincms3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/bringing-feincms-and-django-content-editorfeincms3-closer-together/"&gt;Bringing FeinCMS and django-content-editor/feincms3 closer together&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a link to all posts in the &lt;a href="https://406.ch/writing/category-feincms/?o=chronological"&gt;feincms category&lt;/a&gt; if you want to follow along.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>